<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 ./changes.xsd">
	<properties>
		<title>HAPI TestPanel</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<release version="2.1.0" date="TBD">
            <action type="fix">
            	Correct a NullPointerException when opening a message from a text file
            </action>
            <action type="fix">
            	Prevent a failure to autosave messages when TestPanel is closing if the charset has not been selected
            </action>
      </release>
		<release version="2.0.1" date="">
            <action type="fix" dev="Olaf Zevenboom">
            	Add a mode to send a message or a group of messages more than once in a row
            	(for load testing, stress testing, etc.)
            </action>
		    <action type="fix" dev="Thomas Robinson">
            	Make highlights clear properly when switching to XML format, or moving
            	around in XML documents.
            </action>
            <action type="fix">
            	Show currently highlighted message in text editor component on Windows platform. For some reason,
            	the Windows L&amp;F was preventing this. 
            </action>
            <action type="fix">
            	Incoming connections (on the left hand side) don't show new received message notification
            	after they have been selected and then deselected. 
            </action>
            <action type="fix">
            	Performance tweak to make navigating around the message editor (e.g. with arrow keys)
            	much more responsive
            </action>
            <action type="add">
                When TestPanel is restarted, the main window returns to the same message/connection that
                was selected when TestPanel was last closed.
            </action>
            <action type="add">
                Message tree values now have a tooltip which shows the entire value.
            </action>
            <action type="add">
                While sending messages, current throughput and send/receive time is shown
            </action>
		</release>
        <release version="2.0" date="2012-07-16">
            <action type="fix">
            	Fix a permission error that prevented creating a new message if the
            	HAPI id_file ever gets corrupted
            </action>
            <action type="add">
            	Add HL7 v2 File Diff to Tools Menu: This feature allows two
            	files containg a series of HL7 messages to be compared for
            	semantic differences, with any differences presented in context
            	of the message.
            </action>
            <action type="add">
            	Message editor now remembers which interface was last used to send specific 
            	messages to.
            </action>
            <action type="fix">
                Conformance Profile Group editor didn't show first entry in list of
                Table Files. Thanks to Thomas Robinson for reporting!
            </action>
            <action type="fix">
                Files being re-opened when TestPanel is restarted to not respect the previously chosen charset,
                which can lead to corruption. 
            </action>
            <action type="fix">
                Open File dialog allows user to select a charset 
            </action>
            <action>
                Recent messages submenu in File menu doesn't show currently open files                
            </action>
        </release>
	    <release version="2.0-beta3" date="2012-02-14">
            <action type="fix">
            	Modifying a message via the message tree with another message immediately
            	following it could corrupt the following message
            </action>
            <action type="fix" issue="3488484" dev="Jens Villadsen">
            	Fix a null pointer exception on startup if a previously open file has been deleted
            </action>
            <action type="add">
            	Make the editor window highlight the selected message part in a more obvious way
            	when a node is selected in the message tree
            </action>
		</release>
        <release version="2.0-beta2" date="2012-02-03">
            <action type="fix">
            	Fix issue where some populated nodes don't show up in message tree when
            	a conformance profile is activated
            </action>
            <action type="fix">
            	Message list on left side now shows file names if the file has been saved
            </action>
            <action type="add">
            	Add "clear" button to the activity window displayed when messages are being transmitted,
            	and remove tooltips, which are mostly huge and annoying.
            </action>
            <action type="fix">
            	Navigating the message tree using the keyboard is now possible
            </action>
            <action type="add">
            	Introduce profile groups
            </action>
            <action type="add">
            	Add a spinner to show progress while the message tree is being created or updated (including message validation)
            </action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0-beta1" date="2012-01-22">
			<action type="update">Initial Release</action>
		</release>
	</body>
</document>
