<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

	<properties>
		<title>HAPI TestPanel</title>
		<author email="jamesagnew@users.sourceforge.net">John Doe</author>
	</properties>

	<body>

		<!-- The body of the document contains a number of sections -->
		<section name="HAPI TestPanel">

			<b>Jump to...</b>

			<macro name="toc">
			  <param name="section" value="2"/>
			  <param name="fromDepth" value="0"/>
			  <param name="toDepth" value="4"/>
			</macro>

			<p>
				The HAPI TestPanel is a full featured HL7 message editor,
				transmitter and receiver. This software is still an alpha
				release, so please use it with caution!
			</p>
			
			<p>
				This software can be used to test applications which use the
				HAPI Java API, but it can also be used to test applications which
				don't! It is also intended to be a showcase for HAPI's many features.
			</p>
			
			<img src="images/testpanel_mainwindow.png" alt="Main Window"/>
			
		</section>

		<section name="Installing TestPanel">
		
			<subsection name="Using WebStart">
				
				<p>
					The easiest way to install TestPanel is using Java WebStart. To do this,
					<a href="http://hl7api.sourceforge.net/hapi-testpanel/jnlp/launch.jnlp">click here</a>.
				</p>
				<p>
					Alternately, an application bundle is available for Mac/OSX, and an executable
					JAR is available for Windows/Linux. To access these,
					<a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/hl7api/files/hapi-testpanel">click here</a>.
					(Help Wanted: If you have any experience in bundling desktop applications for Windows,
					we could use your help!)
				</p>
				
			</subsection>
		
		</section>

		<section name="Getting Started">

			<p>
				Once the application has started, populate it with test data by
				entering the "Test" menu and 
				clicking "Populate TestPanel with Sample Message and Connections". 
			</p>
		
			<p>
				This creates a receiving connection (a connection which receives messages)
				on a randomly assigned port. It also creates a sending connection (a 
				connection which sends messages) to that same port, so that you can send
				a message to yourself. It then creates a sample message for you to send.
			</p>
			
			<subsection name="Sending a message to yourself">

				<p>
					First, choose the receiving connection by clicking on it's name (near 
					the bottom left of the window). When the settings dialog opens,
					click "start".
				</p>
				
				<p>
					Then, choose the message to send by clicking on the message in the
					message list (near the top left of the window). Now, click send.
				</p>

			</subsection>
			
			<p>
				This help document is not yet complete. Want to help finish it?
				Get in touch!
			</p>
			
			
		</section>

	</body>

</document>
